Guide to the Camp Kinderland Records TAM.439
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Camp Kinderland Records
1923-2011
TAM.439
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
8.0 linear feet (8 boxes)
Camp Kinderland was founded on Sylvan Lake in Hopewell Junction, NY in 1923 by members of the Workmen’s Circle who worked in the organization’s New York City schools. The camp’s founders sought to create a summer youth camp that would not only provide a recreational escape for the children of working people from the tenements of New York City, but also one whose culture would encourage and foster a commitment to socially progressive activism and the embracing of a rich Jewish secular tradition. The camp's founders, including some activists in the Communist Party, were associated with the left wing of the Workermen's Circle. From 1930 the Camp operated under the auspices of a branch of the International Workers order. In the 1950s, under the pressure of New York State "anti-subversive" investigations, it was incorporated independently. The collection contains administrative records (including legal and financial records, property and maintenance files, registration and membership records), files relating to Camp Kinderland's cultural programs both in and out of season, publicity materials and oral histories.
Camp "Kinderland" (Hopewell Junction, N.Y.).
Box 1-8
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Camp Kinderland Photographs. (PHOTOS 267)
Camp Wo-Chi-Ca Photographs. (PHOTOS 156)
Camp Wo-Chi-Ca Records. (TAM 206)
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 7 series:
Series I: Administrative Records, 1925-2006; Series II: Financial Records, 1934-1996; Series III: Property and Maintenance Records, 1933-1999; Series IV: Registration and Membership Office Records, 1953-2008; Series V: Cultural Programs, 1937-2003; Series VI: Publicity, 1947-2007; Series VII: Off-Season Programs, 1957-2009.
Files are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Historical/Biographical Note
Camp Kinderland was founded on Sylvan Lake in Hopewell Junction, NY in 1923 by members of The Workmen’s Circle who worked in the organization’s New York City Schools. The camp’s founders sought to create a summer youth camp that would not only provide a recreational escape for the children of working people from the tenements of New York City, but also encourage and foster a commitment to socially progressive activism and the embracing of a rich Jewish secular tradition. Responding to a growing demand from parents of campers and other visitors, many of whom had already taken to sleeping on dining-hall floors, Kinderland would quickly establish an adult wing, Camp Lakeland.
Both the youth and adult camps provide summer recreation opportunities found at most camps. Recreational activities include swimming, hiking, camping and outdoor sports, as well as cultural activities such as music, drama, dance and the arts. The camp’s culture is both officially and informally grounded in the Jewish tradition of progressive activism, with its core values of peace, social justice, activism, civil rights, Yiddishkeit, and friendship.
From less than one hundred campers in its first year, Camp Kinderland grew quickly, and by 1933 close to 500 children filled over thirty bungalows and tent groupings. In 1930, the leftist wing of the Workmen’s Circle, along with Camp Kinderland, split off to form the International Worker’s Order (IWO). The Camp was formally sponsored by the Jewish People’s Fraternal Order of the IWO. Although New York State declared the IWO a “Communist-allied” organization in 1954 and revoked its charter, Camp Kinderland was able to continue by incorporating independently. Kinderland did come under scrutiny from the FBI as a Communist-affiliated organization, and its manager, David Greene, was called to testify before the House Committee on Unamerican Activites in 1955.
In 1971, after years of increasing county taxes and declining numbers of campers, the board and directors sold the Camp’s property in Hopewell Junction and relocated to a rented property in Fitchville, Connecticut. After five years of renting sites for the Camp in Connecticut, Pennsylvania and New York, Kinderland purchased property in 1976 in Tolland, Massachusetts. In the same year camp was re-incorporated by the state of NY, with offices at 1 Union Square in Manhattan. Among the prominent participants in the Camp's cultural program have been Paul Robeson and Pete Seeger, and notable alumni include Chesa Boudin, Jules Dassin, Max Kellerman, Spencer Ackerman and Marisa Tomei.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains administrative records (including financial records, property and maintenance records, registration and membership records), and records relating to Camp Kinderland's cultural programs both in and out of season, publicity materials and oral histories. These materials document the the founding, incorporation history, physical plant, staffing and day to day operations of Camp Kinderland, at its various locations. The Camp's underlying political commitments, values and cultural programs are also documented. A number of files illustrate the Camp's reunions, and the continuing ties it maintained with several generations of former campers.
Provenance
The Camp Kinderland Records were donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive by Camp Kinderland in 2008.
Camp "Kinderland" (Hopewell Junction, N.Y.).; Seeger, Pete, 1919-; Segal, Edith, 1902-; Suller, Elsie.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities.; Camps |z Massachusetts |x History |y 20th century.; Camps |z New York (State) |x History |y 20th century.; Camps |z Pennsylvania.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Minutes.; Socialists |z United States |x Recreation.; Songbooks.
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1925-2006.
  Scope and Content Note
  The first series of the collection contains the camp’s administrative records; Executive meeting minutes, office records, program audits, and other materials related to the running of the camp. This series includes legal records relating to New York State's investigation of Kinderland as an alleged subversive institution. Of particular interest are transcripts from the State Legislative Committee hearings conducted in 1955 with the Camp’s director/instructors David Greene and Edith Segal. A copy of Kinderland’s FBI file, obtained via a Freedom of Information Act request, is also in this series.
  - Administrative Meetings: Minutes, 1925-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Meetings: Minutes, 1980-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Records: Friends of Camp Kinderland Committee, Membership, 1960-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Records: General, 1926-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Records, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - By-Laws and Constitution, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conferences, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conferences: Annual, Administrative, 1958-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Corporate Records (bound, includes Board of Director's and Administrative Committee Minutes and Audit Reports), 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Corporate Records (bound, includes Board of Director's and Executive Committee Minutes), 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Greene, David: State and Federal Investigation, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - FBI Investigation, 1955-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Itkowitz, Fay: A Brief History of Camp Kinderland, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 12A)
  - Joint Legislative Committee to Study Charitable and Philanthropic Agencies and Organizations (NY State): General, 1951-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Joint Legislative Committee to Study Charitable and Philanthropic Agencies and Organizations (NY State): Minutes of Hearing, Apr 22, 1955-Apr 24, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Executive Board/Board of Directors, 1956-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Executive Board/Board of Directors, 1992-2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Legal Records: Not-for-Profit Incorporation, 1925-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Member in Good Standing Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Seasonal/Annual Reports: Cultural/Programmatic, 1970-1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Seasonal/Annual Reports: Financial/Administrative, 1956-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Financial Records, 1934-1996.
  Series II contains financial materials, including banking records and fundraising drives conducted.
  - Camp Lakeland Inc.: Banking Records, Loans, 1941-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Camp Lakeland Inc.: Banking Records, Loans, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records: Budget, Banking, Assets, 1978-1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Financial Reports, 1926-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fundraising: Donor Correspondence, 1986-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fundraising: General, 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Fundraising: Phonathons, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ledger: Mortgage Agreement with International Workers Order; By-laws of Camp Kinderland Associates, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Stock Certificate Book: New Kinderland Camp Corp. (bound), 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series III: Property and Maintenance Records, 1933-1999.
  This series contains property records for the various camp sites which Kinderland called home. Together the folders provide a narrative of sorts for the camp’s location over the years; its origins at Hopewell Junction’s Sylvan Lake, from 1923 to 1971, the closing of that property and the inter-site years, when Kinderland spent Summers in Connecticut and Pennsylvania, and finally, the settlement of the camp at it’s current home in Tolland, Massachusetts, in 1976. This series also contains maintenance records related to the physical and structural caretaking of the camp site and construction projects. In large part, this material relates to the building of a new and extensive dining hall in Tolland, beginning around 1994 and completed for use in the Summer of 1998.
  - Fitchville, CT Property, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Honesdale, PA Property, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Inter-Site Years, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Maintenance: Audits, Projects, Proposals, and Fundraising Records, 1996-1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - New Dining Hall: Construction, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - New Dining Hall: Construction, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - New Dining Hall: Construction, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - New Dining Hall: Construction, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - New Dining Hall: Equipment and Supplies Installation, 1994-1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New Dining Hall: Equipment and Supplies Installation, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - New Dining Hall: Fundraising, 1994-1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - New Dining Hall: Specs, Illustrations, and Maps, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sylvan Lake/Hopewell Junction: Sale of Propertry, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sylvan Lake/Hopewell Junction: Legal, Financial, Administrative Records, 1963-1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sylvan Lake: Mortgage Records (I), 1954-1978 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Sylvan Lake: Mortgage Records (II), 1954-1978 (Box 3, Folder 15A)
  - Sylvan Lake: Property Records, 1933-1963 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Tolland, MA: Camp Site Transition, 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Tolland, MA: Property Purchase Records, 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series IV: Registration and Membership Office Records, 1953-2010., 1953-2008
  Series IV contains office records for registration of campers and staff, and more general records for membership to the camp, including records of enrollment, hiring, and directories of campers. Of note is a file on the "Chris Nelson Scholarship Fund," created in memory of a camper killed in an automobile accident on his way home from camp. Beginning in the 1970s this fund was used to provide financial aid to send children to Kinderland.
  - Camper/Staff Directories, 1976-1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Camper/Staff Directories, 1982-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Camper/Staff Directories, 1991-2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Parents, Campers, Friends, 1976-1996 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Counselor-in-Training Program, 1971-1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Directories, 1990-2003 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Directories, 2004-2010 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Nelson, Chris: Scholarship Fund, 1971-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Program Information for Parents and Campers, 1953-1974 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Registration, 1954-2008 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Staff Applications and Hiring, 1956-1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Staff Manuals, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Staff Manuals: Non-Kinderland, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Staff Materials, 1953-1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Series V: Cultural Program, 1937-2003.
  Series V contains material and records related to Kinderland's cultural activities. Files include programs for the Olympics, a competitive athletic activity held annually in place of “color wars” or track meets. The series also includes reading materials, performance pieces and plays, song sheets, records of past projects for use by campers and staff, journals, camp-produced newsletters, trip logs, letters, records of exercises and activities, and art projects. The journal folders, which contain large sections in Yiddish, provide an intimate view of the character of the camp and the people who participated in it over the years.
  - Camp Lakeland Program Materials, 1952-1956 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Camper Cultural Projects: Art, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Cultural Program: General, 1946-1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Cultural Program: General, 1955-1969 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Cultural Program: General, 1971-2001 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Cultural Program: Olympics, 1954-1981 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cultural Projects: Camper-Produced Journals/Newsletters, 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Cultural Projects: Camper-Produced Journals/Newsletters, 1953-1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Cultural Projects: Camper-Produced Journals/Newsletters, 1969-2003 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Cultural Projects: Holocaust Commemoration, Camper Projects and Art, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Cultural Projects: Olympics Art by Campers, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Kindertog, 1937-1954 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Segal, Edith: Cultural Contributions, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Songsheets I, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Songsheets II, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Songsheets III, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Series VI: Publicity, 1947-2007.
  Series VI contains the records of the public face of the Camp, including its own advertisements and newsletters, as well as general media coverage of the Camp and its programs.
  - Advertisements for Kinderland/Lakeland, 1950s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - History, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Kinderschule Graduation, June 5, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 5A)
  - Newsletters, 1947-2011 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Press, 1942-1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Press, 1994-2006 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Public Relations: Advertising, 1967-1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Public Relations: Invitations/Appeals, 1967-1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Off-season Programs, 1957-2009.
  Series VII contains materials related to Kinderland activities, events, and programs conducted outside of the summer season. In the first part are the records of some of the Camp’s many reunions, which often served as fundraisers to benefit the Camp. In these files are the records of three large reunions, held on Kinderland’s 56th, 60th, and 75th anniversaries. Also in this series are the records of Kinderland cultural and recreational events; dances, protests and demonstrations, film screenings, and Passover seders among them. In addition, there are the records of benefit concerts, retirement celebrations, and memorials organized by and for the Camp during the off-season months.
  - 56th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning (I), 1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 56th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning (II), 1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 56th Anniversary: Program Materials (I), 1979 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 56th Anniversary: Program Materials (II), 1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 60th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning Records, “Biz 120” Campaign, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 60th Anniversary: Program Materials, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 75th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning (I), 1999 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 75th Anniversary: Financial, Legal, Planning (II), 1999 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 75th Anniversary: Journal, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - 75th Anniversary: Program Materials, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - 75th Anniversary: Publicity, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Asimolar, CA Reunion, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Camp Kinderland Cookbook, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Camp Lakeland: Anniversaries, Reunions, Fundraising Events, 1967-1971 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Havana, Cuba Trip, Apr 2000 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Klebansky, Chaike: Memorial, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Near, Holly: Benefit Concert, Mar 11, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Off-season Activities: General, 1954-2009 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Passover Haggadahs, 2002-2011 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Reunions, 1957-1990 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Rittel Children's Boutique (Woodstock, NY): Guest Register (photocopy), 1974-1992 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Seeger, Pete: Benefit Concert, Mar 14, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Seeger, Pete: Postcards, 1996-1997 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Segal, Edith: Memorial, Oct 26, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Suller, Elsie: Memorial, May 12, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Suller, Elsie: Retirement Event, May 20, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Undzer Zhurnal (Our Journal), 2011 (Box 8, Folder 15A)
  - Yackle Journal, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Yackles: 60th Anniversary Reunion, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)